<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3CR3//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3CR3/docbookx.dtd">
<book lang="en">
  <bookinfo>
    <title>OTHERobjects CMS</title>

    <subtitle>Site Designer Guide</subtitle>

    <releaseinfo>0.3</releaseinfo>
  </bookinfo>

  <toc></toc>

  <preface id="preface">
    <title>Preface</title>

    <section id="section-why-another-framework">
      <title>Who is this guide for?</title>

      <para>This guide is for users who wish to build their own website. It
      covers installing and runnign OTHERobjects, configuring data types and
      building templates and adding action logic to events and scheduled
      tasks.</para>

      <para>For information on adding content and maintaining an existing site
      please see the User Guide.</para>

      <para>Move advanced users wishing to extend OTHERobjects should read the
      Developer Guide.</para>
    </section>
  </preface>

  <chapter id="chapter-using-the-framework">
    <title>Getting started</title>

    <para>Installing OTHERobjects</para>

    <para>Starting OTHERobjects</para>

    <para>Setting up admin user (for more info see Users and permissions
    chapter).</para>
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <title>Building templates</title>

    <para></para>
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <title>Users and permissions</title>

    <para></para>
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <title>Scheduling tasks</title>

    <para>How to create scheduled tasks.</para>

    <para>Setting the user to run as.</para>

    <para>How to configuer timings. See:
    http://quartz.sourceforge.net/javadoc/org/quartz/CronTrigger.html</para>
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <title>Common features</title>

    <note>
      <para>This may become a separate Patterns Guide.</para>
    </note>

    <para>Print versions</para>

    <para>Text only</para>

    <para>Calendaring</para>

    <para>Commenting</para>

    <para>Header data</para>

    <para>Images and links</para>

    <para>Navigation</para>
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <title>Writing tests</title>

    <para>A stable and high-quality website requires thorough testing. All too
    often this testing is on the form "Does this page look sort of right?" or
    "Well It worked for me when I built it so it's OK to go live". Whilst this
    approach will work for very simple sites, as soon as the complexity
    increases there just isn't time to look at every page and try every action
    manually after each change. This in where automated testing comes
    in.</para>

    <para>People who are new to testing often bemoan the amount of time they
    spend writing tests, especially at first when the tools and techniques are
    new and need to be mastered. This, however, is a small price to pay to
    reduce the time spent debugging and fixing broken code. And as the testign
    techniques become more familiar the tests become correspondingly easier to
    write.</para>

    <section>
      <title>What needs testing</title>

      <para>In a word: everything. </para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Testing scripts</title>

      <para></para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Testing templates</title>

      <para></para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Functional testing</title>

      <para></para>
    </section>
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <title>Improving performance</title>

    <para>OTHERobjects uses caching at several levels to keep your site
    peforming well even under heavy loads. However, it is important to
    understand how the caching works in order to get the best performance out
    of it.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Understanding caching</title>

      <para></para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Monitoring page performance</title>

      <para>To view the performance characteristics of a page press the Escape
      key. A dialog will appear showing the major events that occured whilst
      building the page and how long they took.</para>

      <figure>
        <title>Performance statistics dialog. Press Escape to show.</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/performance-stats-dialog.png"
                       scale="50" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>TODO Warning indicator on pages with heavy loads eg &gt; 100
      calls, or &gt; 5 seconds.</para>
    </section>
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <title>Common problems</title>

    <para>Something already runnign on the port?</para>

    <section>
      <title></title>

      <para></para>
    </section>
  </chapter>
</book>