<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3CR3//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3CR3/docbookx.dtd">
<book lang="en">
  <bookinfo>
    <title>Open sourcing OTHERobjects</title>

    <subtitle>The why and the how</subtitle>

    <releaseinfo>0.2</releaseinfo>
  </bookinfo>

  <toc></toc>

  <preface id="preface">
    <title>What we want to do</title>

    <section>
      <title>Who is this guide for?</title>

      <para>We would like to release OTHERobjects and the rest on our software
      stack (including OTHERcommerce and OTHERclicks) as open-source software.
      Other users will be able to download the software and use it to build
      websites. </para>

      <para>The biggest danger facing an open-source project in irrelevance.
      By providing a high quality and complete Java based software stack we
      think we could get a fair sized community relatively quickly. Key to
      that though is releasing unique and useful software. </para>

      <para>Whilst there are a few other open source Java CMS systems they
      lack polish. There are only a couple of open source Java eCommerce
      systems and they are not widely adopted. </para>
    </section>
  </preface>

  <chapter>
    <title>Why we should do it</title>

    <para></para>

    <section>
      <title>Excellent publicity </title>

      <para>This gives a real story to shout about. It will increase our
      profile in the industry and make potential clients aware of us. </para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Gives us a technical reputation </title>

      <para>Currently we have no real technical reputation. By creating and
      championing an open source project we could gain a reputation as a very
      strong development shop. It puts us ahead of the curve -- no other
      agencies are doing this. </para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Feedback and ideas from external users </title>

      <para>By making OO available for others to use we will receive feedback
      from them. They will bring new ideas and new ways of building sites that
      we won't have thought of. </para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Feedback from experienced programmers </title>

      <para>There are almost certainly much better ways of doing some of the
      things we have done. As an open source project we would receive feedback
      and advice from other experienced programmers. </para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Our work done by external developers</title>

      <para>Other users of OO will report problems and ask for new features.
      Some of them will fix the problems and build the features themselves,
      saving us time and effort. If other developers adopt OO seriously they
      may contribute significant amounts of useful code -- in effect sharing
      the development costs. </para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Feedback from associated projects </title>

      <para>The other projects that we use in OTHERobjects (Hibernate,
      Velocity) have considerable experience integrating with projects like
      web:kit. By making our code open source we can show them how we have
      approached the problem and get their feedback. </para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Better access to developers of associated projects </title>

      <para>There are times when we would like changes made to associated
      projects. As an open source project we would stand a much better chance
      of having our opinions heard and acted on. </para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Incentive to write better code and documentation</title>

      <para>Developing code with the knowledge that it will be seen by others
      encourages you to question, justify and document your decisions. The
      result is better, more secure and more maintainable code. </para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Vulnerabilities can be discovered, reported and fixed</title>

      <para>Peer review is the standard methodology for security related
      projects. Other developers will be able to check our code and notify us
      of any security issues. </para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Better for education</title>

      <para>If the code is open source it is much easier to use it in articles
      and lectures. Students or readers can download OO, see how it works and
      start using it. They could choose to base projects around it, providing
      us with another pool of developers. </para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Finding employees</title>

      <para>Our standard no-thank-you letter to job applicants should contain
      an invitation to get involved with the OO project. Those who do get
      involved and produce good code could be employed at a later date. Good
      developers may also be drawn to us by OO project making it easier to
      recruit. </para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Finding freelancers</title>

      <para>With a closed source CMS only our developers will know how to use
      it. Anyone who starts using our open-source CMS becomes a potential
      freelancer who can help us out during busy periods. </para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Higher profile for our developers</title>

      <para>Designers have their work on constant display but developers work
      is hidden. Open source is an opportunity for the OTHER media to show off
      the quality of its technical team.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Reassure clients who are worried about lock-in</title>

      <para>A common concern from larger clients is that they are locked in to
      our proprietary CMS. Using an open-source CMS (especially one with a
      growing user base) will alleviate these fears.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>People who adopt OO become potential clients</title>

      <para>Organisations who start using OO for their sites will eventually
      need new features for their sites. The natural supplier services to
      these companies will be the OTHER media.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Clients who understand open source will like us more</title>

      <para>Those clients who understand open source (and that includes large
      corporations and governments) will know why we have chosen to open
      source our code and like us for it.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Clients who have technical knowledge will respect us more</title>

      <para>Larger clients will have technical employees who will be able to
      see the scale and quality of what we have developed.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Access to commercial development tools at no cost</title>

      <para>Several development tools vendors provide free licenses to
      open-source projects. Examples include Yourkit Profiler (which makes it
      easy to find performance bottlenecks), Clover (which measures how much
      of your code is excised in tests) and Fisheye (which provides detailed
      information about the source code repository). To purchase these tools
      would cost thousands of dollars.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>It makes us more attractive to investors</title>

      <para>Open source is a major part of many new companies. Being the owner
      of a widely used open source project makes us a much more interesting
      company to potential investors.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Give back some of what we're taking</title>

      <para>OO wouldn't have be possible without open source. We are now
      completely dependent on other open source projects. Since we have gained
      so much from open source we have a moral duty to give back in some
      way.</para>
    </section>
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <title>Why we should think carefully about this</title>

    <para>Some reasons against open-sourcing our software.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Explaining to clients why our software is free</title>

      <para>We are already charging them for a lot of free stuff: Linux,
      Apache, Java, postgres, velocity, hibernate. OO would represent a tiny
      fraction of the free code we are using. And the majority of our clients
      are not paying for OO anyway. </para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Hackers can spot vulnerabilities in the code and exploit them
      </title>

      <para>By making out code available developers can spot the weaknesses.
      Instead of reporting them they may choose to exploit them. However, the
      general consensus in the security community is that hackers will find
      the weaknesses anyway and that it is better to have the code open so
      that people can help find and fix the weakness. We should also consider
      a third-party security audit before the initial release. </para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Competing agencies may use OTHERobjects (and pitch against us)
      </title>

      <para>If this is a concern we should always inform clients that we have
      an open source CMS that we have developed and that other agencies are
      free to use it. If we demo our system it will be pretty obvious if
      another company is using a rebranded version of our CMS. And in this
      situation we would have a considerable technical advantage (as the
      creators not just the users) of a CMS. A more likely scenario is that
      other agencies use our CMS for projects that we don't pitch for and
      develop new and useful plugins for us.</para>
    </section>
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <title>Licensing options</title>

    <para>There are 2 dominant types of open source licences.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Apache/BSD/MIT Licenses</title>

      <para>“You are free to use this code however you want.” </para>

      <para>This is arguably the most “open” open source projects. All the
      open source components included in OO5 are licensed under this type of
      license which allows us to resell OO without restrictions. A BSD
      licensed project can be used in any commercial project with no
      restrictions.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>GNU Public License</title>

      <para>“If you use this code in your project, then you must also
      open-source your project”</para>

      <para>This license effectively prevents the code being used in
      commercial products. Whilst there in nothing in the license that
      specifically prevents the code being modified and sold as a product, if
      this does happen then the code of the commercial product would be
      required to be open source, thus allowing others to distribute it free
      of charge. As a consequence of this, any enhancements made by third
      parties to our code would need to be released publicly and we could
      incorporate them into future versions. We recommend licensing
      OTHERobjects under the GPL. Future licensing options As the copyright
      holder to all the code we would have the option of changing the
      licensing policy at any time. For example, we could offer an
      unrestricted commercial license that would allow other companies to use
      our code in their projects. We would also have the right to stop
      releasing OO as open-source. However, past releases would always remain
      open.</para>
    </section>
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <title>Copyright and trademark issues</title>

    <para>We recommend that the copyright to all the code in OTHERobjects is
    owned by the OTHER media (or OTHERworks?). All contributors to the code
    base would be asked to assign the copyright of their code over to the
    OTHER media. </para>

    <para>The trademarks for the name (and logos?) for OTHERobjects would
    continue to be held by the OTHER media. We would have the right to
    restrict their usage if we so wished. See
    http://www.ubuntu.com/aboutus/trademarkpolicy for an example of how
    another projects do this. </para>
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <title>How to do it</title>

    <para>Code quality</para>

    <para>Documentation</para>

    <para>Project website</para>

    <para>Demo videos</para>

    <para>Training sessions</para>

    <para></para>
  </chapter>

  <appendix>
    <title>Further reading</title>

    <para>Open Source Initiative: http://www.opensource.org/ </para>

    <para>Producing Open Source Software by Karl Fogel:
    http://producingoss.com/ </para>

    <para></para>
  </appendix>
</book>