<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3CR3//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3CR3/docbookx.dtd">
<book lang="en">
  <bookinfo>
    <title>OTHERobjects CMS</title>

    <subtitle>User Guide</subtitle>

    <releaseinfo>0.5</releaseinfo>
  </bookinfo>

  <toc></toc>

  <preface id="preface">
    <title>Preface</title>

    <section>
      <title>Who is this guide for?</title>

      <para>This guide is for users of the OTHERobjects CMS. You wil already
      have a working site installed and built. This guide will cover the
      management or the site and it's content.</para>
    </section>
  </preface>

  <chapter>
    <title>What is OTHERobects?</title>

    <para>[Brief overview of what a CMS is and how it works]</para>
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <title>Using the libraries</title>

    <para>Intro</para>

    <section>
      <title>Link library</title>

      <para>You can put links in without using the library. This is preferred
      for links that are not used more than once. Advantages: easily change +
      easily select.</para>
    </section>
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <title>Publishing and workflow</title>

    <para></para>

    <section>
      <title>Publishing/Unpublishing task</title>

      <para>This OO task is run automatically, publishing all content which
      has not been published and where the embargo date is before the current
      date and time (at the moment when the task runs) or is not set, and the
      expiry date is after the current date and time or is not set. </para>

      <para>This task also unpublishes all expired content, i.e., all
      published content where the expiry date is set and is &lt;= current date
      and time. </para>
    </section>
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <title>Creating content</title>

    <para>Creating content is easy.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Wiki Syntax</title>

      <para>We use a simplified wiki syntax to control the formatting of
      textual. This has several advantages (realiable cross browser, standards
      compliant markup, reliable copy and paste, create offline, repuprose as
      non-HTML).</para>

      <para>We use the Textile syntax. A full reference is available here:
      http://hobix.com/textile/ or see our quick reference card TODO.</para>

      <para>The features that are not supported as of July 2009 are:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Table cell alignment: center, bottom</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Some entity replacement doesn't work (eg dashes, elipsis,
          smart quotes)</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Alt text on images is buggy</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Link aliases work but leave the link definition visible</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <title>Editing content</title>

    <para></para>
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <title>Maintenance and information</title>

    <para></para>

    <sect1>
      <title>Running Jobs</title>

      <para>On the debug view, specifically /otherobjects/debug/scheduler, you
      can see the currently active job triggers and running jobs.</para>

      <para>Triggers can be stopped and restarted, preventing or scheduling
      the next fire of the job.</para>

      <para>Running jobs can be stopped.</para>
    </sect1>
  </chapter>
</book>
